Guide to the Gay and Lesbian Education Fund records, 1977-1994 MS2052
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gay and Lesbian Education Fund records
1977-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gay and Lesbian Education Fund
MS2052
5 Linear Feet
Collection documents on the establishment and the work of the Gay and Lesbian Education Fund located in Washington, D.C. (GALEF). Originally established in 1980 as the Gay Activist Alliance Education Fund (GAAEF), the goals set forth by the organization was to help educate the general public, specifically the straight community, about gays and lesbians by sponsoring and supporting events and programs.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to The George Washington University by GALEF in 1999.
Historical Note
The Gay and Lesbian Education Fund was founded in Washington, D.C. in 1980. Originally called the Gay Activists Alliance Education Fund, an offshoot of the Gay Activists Alliance, the organization's mission was to secure full rights and privileges for gays by educating heterosexual American citizens about gay concerns. The founding members of the organization were Harvey Yampolsky, Mayo Lee, Delores Cole, Alberto Bastida, Aundrea Scott, Vince Turner, Alexa Freeman, Michael Waters and Tom Ainora. GALEF located its registered office at 1469 Church St. NW. Melvin Boozer, one of the incorporators of GALEF's by-laws and president of the Gay Activists Alliance, was the initial registered agent at this address. Throughout the 1980s and 1990s, GALEF took part in and supported various projects to help further their ideals. A few of these projects were aimed at the college student population at campuses such as George Washington, Georgetown and American University.
In the early 1990s, the organization was involved in a highly visible and controversial Metro advertising campaign. The campaign was intended to create awareness that homosexuals were also people with families. The controversy was centered on how the ads were presented: "The next time you think 'faggot' or 'dyke,' remember…we belong to someone's family, perhaps yours." The main goal that GALEF wanted to achieve was to let the straight community know that any discrimination or harm directed at homosexuals based on hate could also affect an individual within their own family.
By the mid-1990s, GALEF was continuing its practice of supporting individuals or groups with projects that helped further the crusade for equal rights for gays.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection of materials focuses on the establishment and the work of the Gay and Lesbian Education Fund located in Washington, D.C. (GALEF). Originally established in 1980 as the Gay Activist Alliance Education Fund (GAAEF), the goals set forth by the organization was to help educate the general public, specifically the straight community, about gays and lesbians by sponsoring and supporting events and programs.
Housed in 9 document boxes, the collection measures approximately five linear feet. The collection covers the period from 1977-1995. The bulk of the collection is dated from 1980 to 1988. Among the items in the collection are correspondence to and from the various board members, meeting agendas, meeting minutes, correspondence with affiliate groups, clippings, advertisements and a videotape of the former cable TV show "One in Ten."
Collection Organization
Organized into seven series: Board of Directors, Meeting agendas and minutes, Administrative files, Publications, Audio/Visual, Affiliate organizations, and Miscellaneous.
Washington (D.C.); Lesbians -- Washington (D.C.); Videotapes; Gay men -- Washington (D.C.); Gays; Education; Lesbians; Yampolsky, Harvey; Waters, Michael; Gay and Lesbian Education Fund
- Board of Directors, 1980-1993; MS2052 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains 12 folders and spans 1980-1993. The folders are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the board member. The first folder consists of the various board member directories over the years.
  - Board Members Directory, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Tom Ainora Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Delores Cole Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tom DePriest Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Susan Donahue Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Susan Donahue Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alexa Freeman Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lorri Jean Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mayo Lee Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kathleen Maloy Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Aundrea Scott Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Debra Waugh Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1980-1994; MS2052 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains three folders spaning the years of 1980-1994. They are arranged chronologically as 1980-1986, 1987-1989 and 1990-1994 respectively.
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Administrative Files, 1980-1994; MS2052 Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of 28 folders arranged alphabetically. The largest group of folders is under the heading "Funding Requests," which consists of five folders arranged chronologically.
  - Bank Statements, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bank Statements, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bank Statements, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contributions, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (Copyright Office), 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Funding Requests, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Funding Requests, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Funding Requests, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Funding Requests, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Funding Requests, 1985-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising, 1980-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Georgetown Law Center-Gay Forum, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Histories, 1980-1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Histories, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lesbian Writers, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Metro Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press Releases, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Resumes, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Signature Cards, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Tax Information, 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tax Information, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Tax Information, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Time Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Publications, 1979-1991; MS2052 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is made up of various newspapers printed by affiliates of GALEF and features articles on gay issues and GALEF ads from 1979, 1990, and 1991. The folder "Our Paper" has an article on the Metro Ad campaign.
  - The New Festival, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Our Paper, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Someone in Your Life, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Special Dandelion, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Audio/Visual, undated; MS2052 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This container consists of a videotape of the final episode of the cable TV show "One in Ten."
  - "One In Ten" Video, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Affiliate Organizations, 1977-1992; MS2052 Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series is housed in 3 document boxes and consists of 60 folders. The largest group of folders belongs to Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG) in 2 folders. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - AID Atlanta, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Alexandria Gay Community Association, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Alexandria Gay Community Association, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - American University Human Diversity League, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Barn Grant Project, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Blue Ridge Lambda Press, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Carl Vogel Foundation, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Catholic University, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Children's Hospital, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Cinema Guild, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Common Capital Fund, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Creative Learning, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - DC Coalition of Black Gays, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - DC Lesbian and Gay Community Services Center, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Food and Friends, Inc., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - The Fund for Human Dignity, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Gay Activists Alliance, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Gay and Lesbian Activists Alliance, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Gay and Lesbian Alumni Association of Georgetown University, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gay and Lesbian Community Action Council, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Gay and Lesbian Military Freedom, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Gay and Lesbian Parents Coalition International, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Gay Men's Health Crisis, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Gay People of Georgetown University, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Gay People's Alliance of GW, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Gay Rescue Mission, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Gay Rights Coalition of Georgetown U vs. Georgetown U, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Gayspring, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Gay Rights National Lobby, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Gay Women's Alternative D.C., 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Health Education Resource Organization, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - High and Dry, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Human Rights Campaign Fund, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - In Our Own Write, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Lambda Community Center, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Lammas, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Lesbian and Gay Organization of Students, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Mautner Project, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Moonforce Media, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Lesbians and Gays, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - National Gay Rights Advocates, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - National Gay Task Force, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National March on Washington/Names Project, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - National Organization of Women, 1977-1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - New Ways Ministry, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Northern Virginia Gay Alliance, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - One in Ten, 1992-1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Open Hands, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, 1983-1990 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, 1983-1993 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Prince George's Community College Gay People's Union, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Police Awareness Project, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Sexual Minority Youth Assistance League, 1983-1993 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Southeastern Conference for Lesbians and Gay Men, 1985-1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - United Way of the Capital Area, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Gay Alliance, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Washington Blade, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Whitman-Walker Gay Hotline, 1983-1993 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Woman's Calendar, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1977-1994; MS2052 Series 7; 1 Linear feet
  This series is housed in 2 document boxes and consists of 13 folders. Twelve of the folders are arranged chronologically and the other folder contains invitation and letterhead art templates.
  - Miscellaneous, 1977-1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980-1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Pride Day), 1981-1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1982-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1983-1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, (Studies/Reports), 1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1985-1991 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986-1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Artwork, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)